many of us think that if we want to add
interactivity to our websites we must
use JavaScript but what we forget is
that because of how powerful CSS can be
sometimes we don't need JavaScript at
all so in this video we are going to
implement a feature that you would think
needs JavaScript using only CSS we will
learn how to build this beautiful
animated hamburger menu only with CSS
let's start with the HTML here we have a
header that contains three elements the
first one is a label element that has
three spans inside of it here is where
we will build and animate the lines of
the burger menu using the four attribute
we are connecting the label with the
checkbox input which means that when the
label is clicked the input will be
checked then we have the title of our
page and finally after the header we
have a nav with the links that the user
will see when the menu is open it does
not look pretty so let's get right to it
with cs first we're going to style the
label and create the lines here all we
are doing is turning the label into a
flex container with a width of 35 pixels
and a height of 25 pixels then we are
making each span into a black line that
is 5 pixels tall with a nice border
radius and a transition for
Transformations as you can see because
the label and the input are connected
when we click on the label on the lines
the input is checked now we are going to
hide the input from the user next we are
going to transform the lines inside of
the label depending if the input is
checked or not to do this we use the has
sudo class here we are checking if the
header that contains all of our elements
has an input that is checked if the
header has an input that is checked we
are rotating the first line 37 degrees
on this Z axis we are scaling the second
line to zero and the third line we are
rotating minus 37 degrees on this Z axis
as well here is how it looks like as you
can see the second line is disappearing
and the first and last one are being
rotated because we want them to be
rotated and form an X we are going to
change their transform Origins by adding
this code before the rotation code as
you can see it looks awesome and next up
we are going to style our Header by
making it into a flex container and
giving it a bit of padding and Shadow
then we are going to add this code all
it does is style the nav the UL and the
links inside of it we give some box
Shadow to the nav and make it have a
width of 30 percent of the size of the
screen we make the UL into a flex
container with paddings and gaps getting
this result next because we want to hide
the navigation we are going to add
transform translate X to move it
horizontally outside of the view of the
user and we are also going to give it a
transition now all is left is to display
the nav when the user clicks on the
hamburger just to remind you this is how
our HTML roughly looks like we have a
header that has an input as a child and
next to the header we have enough what
we want to do is check if the input
inside of the header is checked and if
it is we want to select the brother of
the header the nav and show it to the
users that condition might sound like a
job for the JavaScript but it actually
isn't just by writing this code we can
accomplish the exact same thing here we
are checking if there is a header with a
checked input inside of it and using the
general sibling combinator we are
selecting the nav sibling of the header
then what is left is to unhide the
navigation to get a result like this
and we're done we just built an animated
interactive hamburger menu using only
CSS no JavaScript at all let me know in
the comments if you thought today's
project was only possible using
JavaScript and let me know if you would
like to see me make more videos like
this we could build image galleries
sliders models and more all in pure CSS
thank you for watching as always and
don't forget that if you want to learn
things like JavaScript python react
react native go dark flutter among many
others for absolutely free all you have
to do is click the link below to join
any of our many free courses that you
can take right now for absolutely free
with me click the link below and I will
see you there
see you on the next one bye